<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An argument in defence of the hospitaller of St. Thomas Southwark and of his fellow-servants and friends in the same house</title>
            <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 108 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A63900</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T3300</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R9444</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12924872</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12924872</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95499</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A63900)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95499)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 729:16)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An argument in defence of the hospitaller of St. Thomas Southwark and of his fellow-servants and friends in the same house</title>
                  <author>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 27 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Dedication signed: John Turner.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95499:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ARGUMENT IN DEFENCE OF THE HOSPITALLER OF St. THOMAS SOUTHWARK AND OF His Fellow-Servants and Friends in the ſame Houſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, MDCLXXXIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:95499:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95499:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable The LORD-MAYOR of the City of <hi>London.</hi> and to the Honourable the Court of Aldermen.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Confeſs it was a great ſurprize to me to ſee an Order of Court made for my Ejectment out of this Houſe, in behalf of Mr. Hughes the old Illegall Incumbent, without being firſt heard what I had to ſay for my ſelf, but an after game being better then no Game at all, I haue here made the beſt I can of a bad Market, and have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to lay before you a true ſtate of the Caſe, humbly Entreating you to conſider a little further before you determine finally and Peremtori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the matter, against the only Son of a Citizen like your ſelves, who hath upon that account an equitable pretence to your favour, to ſay nothing of that Justice which every Forreign Petitioner may claim.</p>
            <p>I am ſatisfy'd by the wording of your ſaid Order that you have been miſinformed in the nature of the Controverſy betwixt Mr. Hughes and me, as if he had a legall night accruing to him upon the restitution of the Charter, which I am well aſſured he hath not, and I muſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peal to all indifferent perſons whether I have not ſufficiently prov'd it.</p>
            <p>This is one plain miſapprehenſion, which ſeems to me to evacu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate the ſaid Order, becauſe it is Founded upon it, and if it had not been for that, it appears to me by the expreſs tenour of it, that no ſuch Order had ever been made.</p>
            <p>Another is, that the very Order it ſelf in whatſoever words it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived, ſuppoſeth the Cognizance of this matter to ly immediately and properly before you, which I humbly conceive it doth not, but before the King, till he ſhall be pleas'd to remit it ba<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>k to you, which I ſhall be ſo far from being diſſatisfy'd at, that I repoſe a perfect con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in your goodneſs and justice to me, and I attribute it to no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a miſunderſtanding that any prejudice hath been done me in this affayr. You ought not, my Lord and Gentlemen, to think your ſelves depretiated or undervalu'd in that I ſay, the King is your Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour in thoſe things which belong properly and legally to his inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, when ever he pleaſeth to concern himſelf about them, and which
<pb facs="tcp:95499:3"/> he hath actually taken into his immediate care; King <hi>Charles</hi> the Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, of Glorious and Bleſſed memory, having made a Royall regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation in this Houſe, which cannot be alter'd, as I am humbly of opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, by any leſſer power without the Royall aſſent. Neither is it or can it be thought any diminuition to your Honourable Court, that you ſhould reverſe the ſentence you have past, when even the greateſt Lawyers do frequently alter their minds, and the decrees of Chancery reverſing one another are a plain indication that even they are not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible, whoſe buſineſs and employment it is to underſtand theſe mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters better then others; I leave it to your Lordſhip and the Court to conſider among many other things that appear to be foul againſt him, whether the King if it were referred to his Majeſty to determine, would think it fit to feed with his own proper bread, or to bestow the rewards of Virtue and Obedience upon the Patron and Encomiaſt of his Grandſire's Murther. I wiſh your Lordſhip and the Honourable Court all Happyneſs and proſperity, and I pray as for the Peace of the Land of Canaan in generall, this Land of our Nativity that flows with Milk and Honey, ſo more especially for that of your <hi>Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem,</hi> and that they may proſper that love it. I am, may it pleaſe your Lordſhip and the Honourable Court,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honour's moſt humble, Obedient and obliged Servant John Turner.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95499:3"/>
            <head>THE CASE Between Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> the late pretended Hoſpitaller of St. <hi>Thomas Southwark,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Turner</hi> the preſent Lawfull Incumbent of the ſame, truly Stated.</head>
            <q>
               <lg>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Qui aliquid Statuerit parte inaudita altera</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Aequum licet Statuerit, haut aequus fuerit.</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Ad orbilium Hugonem</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Carpere vel noli nostra, vel Ede tua.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
            </q>
            <p>BEcauſe Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> the late pretended Hoſpitaller of St <hi>Thomas Southwark,</hi> renews his pretenſions upon the Reſtitution of the Charter, as if there were ſuch a neceſſary Connexion betwixt old Men and old Franchiſes, that both muſt unavoidably be reſtored together, therefore I am obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in my own juſt and neceſſary defence, in oppoſition to the falſe and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt inſinuations of an Illegall pretender, to State the whole matter as it is in it ſelf, and to ſuggeſt ſuch conſiderations as do naturally ariſe from it, to keep the Legall poſſeſſion I am in, and to preſerve my ſelf from his intended intruſions and uſurpations upon it.</p>
            <p>Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> was ejected at the ſame time or within a very little while after, that Judgment was had and Entred upon the <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> againſt the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of this Famous City, and therefore this is all which he urgeth in his de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence, the Charer is reſtored, and ſo am I: For we are more nearly related then the two <hi>Tyndaridae,</hi> (Mr <hi>Hughes,</hi> who is a Schoolmaſter knows who I mean) that uſe to live and dye by Turns, and like <hi>Hippocrates</hi> his twins, we both of us ſhare in the ſame common Fate, we laugh in conſort, and we weep together.</p>
            <p>Now to anſwer the more effectually this ſhrewd and Peſtilent objection raiſed againſt me, by a man, that I hope, underſtands Grammer a little better then he ſeems to do Senſe, I beg leave in the firſt place to lay down Mr <hi>Seymours</hi> Caſe, as it was ingeniouſly and truly Stated by himſelf, together with the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pinions of three of the beſt Lawyers and perſons of the moſt unqueſtionable Honour and Integrity, as well as Skill in their Profeſſion, that this Nation affords upon it, and then to raiſe ſuch obſervations from the whole, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect my Caſe as well as his, and to make ſuch other animadverſions and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks upon the Circumſtances peculiar to Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> or me, as the occaſion calls for, which I will do with all the Clearneſs and brevity I am able, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out giving my ſelf that Latitude either for anger or wit, which Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> his provocations would incite me to, or which his untoward Hiſtory would afford me, and in a word, without any other reflection, then what the matters of Fact eſſentiall to my defence do of neceſſity conſtrain me to, reſerving his
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:95499:4"/> life to be written by ſome other hand, if there be any that think it worth their while, or if there be any that can take a pleaſure, which I find to be very un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naturall to me, in expoſing the Faults or Follies or in upbraiding the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexionall misfortunes of little or imprudent men.</p>
            <div type="legal_precedent">
               <head>The Caſe as it was Stated by Mr <hi>S.</hi> and was reſolved by thoſe Learned Gentlemen, is as follows.</head>
               <head type="sub">The Caſe.</head>
               <p>KIng <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th.</hi> having Founded and Endowed <hi>St. Thomas</hi> Hoſpital in <hi>Southwark,</hi> grants the Lands and Revenues belonging to the ſame, to the Mayor Commonalty and Citizens of the City of London, for the benefit of Sick and Lame indigent Perſons, with liberty in his Charter reſerved to viſit and enquire into the management of the truſt.</p>
               <p>According to the uſage of the City, the houſe hath been always govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Citizens and others appointed by the Court of Aldermen, the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours of the houſe for the time being, and the Court of Aldermen, according to the laws and cuſtomes of the City, choſe A their Clerk.</p>
               <p>A <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> being afterwards brought againſt the City and Judgment <hi>Anno</hi> 1683. being thereupon had and enter'd, a Commiſſion was thereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on granted to certain Aldermen and others to regulate the ſaid Hoſpitall, and (<hi>inter alia</hi>) to appoint Governours and Officers of the houſe.</p>
               <p>The ſaid Commiſſioners appoint <hi>B.</hi> to be Clerk of the houſe inſtead of <hi>A.</hi> during the pleaſure of that Court of Commiſſioners.</p>
               <p>His Late Majeſty (<hi>James the Second, when this Caſe was ſtated</hi>) reſtores to the City their antient government, Lands, Tenements, Franchiſes, Priviledges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and ſoon after iſſues out his Proclamation for reſtoring Corporations, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> dated the <hi>17th</hi> of <hi>October</hi> 1688. and diſſolves the ſaid Commiſſion.</p>
               <p>The Caſe being thus ſtated the queſtion is.</p>
               <p>Whether by the ſaid reſtitution of the Charter, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by the ſaid Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation or either of them (B not having been diſcharged of his office by the Commiſſioners) A hath any right to be reſtored to his office of Clerk; eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if the Court of Aldermen hath ſince the reſtitution of the Charter, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed all officers belonging to the City in their reſpective places and the right ſhould appear in that Court to chooſe a Clerk of the ſaid <hi>Hoſpitall.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Sr. Francis Pembertons</hi> reſolution of this Caſe.</p>
               <p>I conceive that the Court of Aldermen being the perſons who authoriſed the Governours of this Hoſpitall by their order, when the Corporation of the City of <hi>London</hi> was diſſolved by the Judgment in the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> the authority of thoſe Governours of the Hoſpitall ceaſed, and they cannot act again without a new order or appointment of the Court of Aldermen, and I conceive the King's proclaimation in <hi>October,</hi> 1688. doth not give any Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to the former Governours of the hoſpitall to Act by the former Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to them given by the former order of the Court of Aldermen, but they ought to be Commiſſionated by a new order, before they Act as Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
               <p>I do apprehend this place of Clerk to the Governours not to be a ſtanding
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95499:4"/> Office, but rather an Employment in it's nature, to be put in or out by the Court of Aldermen if they pleaſe, or, if the Court of Aldermen pleaſe, by the Governors, but ſuch Clerk hath no fixt intereſt in his Employment, and A. hath, I conceive, no right to this place, unleſs be ſhould ſee a new choſen and appointed thereunto by a new Order, and the Kings Proclamation in <hi>October</hi> extends to the enabling and empowering all members &amp; Officers of Corporations to act as they might have done before the <hi>Quo Warranto's</hi> were brought, but that extends only to what they might do, as members or Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of thoſe Corporations, but not to any collaterall matters, which they might have done by virtue of any collaterall Commiſſions derived from thoſe Corporations, as the caſe of theſe Governours and clerk of this Hoſpitall are.</p>
               <p>And I conceive that any Governours of this Hoſpitall appointed by thoſe who acted as Mayor and Aldermen of <hi>London</hi> by virtue of any <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> ſince the Judgment in the <hi>Quo Warranto,</hi> are all diſabled to act or do any thing as Governours, <hi>Letters Patents</hi> to thoſe Mayors and Aldermen being ſet aſide by this Kings Proclamation in <hi>October</hi> laſt, and all the authorities derived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thoſe <hi>Letters Patents,</hi> as depending on them, falling with them.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Fr. Pemberton.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="legal_opinion">
               <head>Mr. <hi>Pollexfen's</hi> Opinion of the ſame <hi>Caſe.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>I conceive that the Clerk hath not any Office or Eſtate, but is only a Servant to the Governours, not within the Charter of reſtitution, or the Proclamation, claiming any legall right or intereſt; but is at will of the Governours, and they at their will and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure may put out or take in, or employ in the place whom they think fit.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>Hen. Pollexfen.</signed>
                  <date>Jan. 11. 1688.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="legal_opinion">
               <head>Sir <hi>John Holt's</hi> Opinion to the ſame purpoſe.</head>
               <p>I conceive that the Clerk not being a Charter Officer is not reſtored by the Kings Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clamation, which extends only to ſuch Officers and members of the Corporations, which were made upon the Originall conſtitution, or by virtue of ſome Charter, but the Clerks place is only a Service or an imployment, which is wholly at the diſpoſall of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours, as they ſhall think fit.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>J. Holt.</signed>
                  <date>January. 15. 88.</date>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <p>The Firſt obſervation I ſhall make from hence ſhall be taken from the ſtate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Caſe it ſelf, wherein it is ſet forth that this Hoſpitall being Found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by King <hi>Edward</hi> the Sixth, the care and truſt of it from time to time was committed to the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the City of <hi>London,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving to himſelf and Succeſſours a liberty to viſit and enquire into the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagement of the truſt, and without any ſuch expreſs reſervation in the <hi>Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> it ſelf, it is but reaſonable and Juſt that in all Hoſpitals that are of Royal Foundation, the King ſhould be the proper and Supream Viſitor, becauſe without this the King and his Succeſſours can have no Aſſurance, but that his Royal Intentions may be diſappointed, his Charity Embezled, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95499:5"/> truſt which is repoſed in certain Perſons for the due management of it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trayed, and beſides the Nature of the thing added to the expreſs reſervation of our Royal Founder in his Charter, the King by Act of Parliament is the Supreme Viſitor of Hoſpitalls and Publick Charities, to ſee that they be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred upon fit and ſuitable objects, and managed by Officers well qualify'd for their Employments.</p>
               <p>Now from hence it appears that the avoidance of the Charter and the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulation of the Hoſpitalls that Followed quickly after it, have no manner of Connexion with each other; it is true indeed that after Judgment was had and entred againſt the Charter, all truſts that were repoſed in the City, as a Corporation, did of neceſſity fall together with it, but yet it is Equally true that the King might have viſited and regulated this and other Hoſpitalls though the Charter had ſtood, he being Supream Viſitor and Inſpector of the ſame, but more Eſpecially of Royal Hoſpitalls that owe their Foundation, derive their Conſtitution, and receive their very being from the Crown, ſo that it is plain that the old Officers might have continued in this houſe, if the King had ſo pleaſed, notwithſtanding the Charter of the City was made void, and that the deſtruction of the Charter had no immediate or conſequentiall Operation upon the Officers of this Houſe, they not being Charter Officers, but Perſons Employ'd in a truſt under the King, whom he may always place or diſplace at his pleaſure, and of whoſe fitneſs and capacity for their reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Employments he is the Supreme and unaccountable Judge. <hi>What there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore can the man do that cometh after the King?</hi> Eccl. 2. 12. Or what inferiour Authority can annull that which the Supreme hath ordered and appointed? To be plain in a Caſe that is not to be dallyed with, my meaning is this, that during the Life of that Glorious &amp; Bleſſed Prince King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, it would not have been Lawful for any inferiour Authority, though the Charter had been reſtored, to diſplace any Officer of his Appointment in this houſe, by virtue of any Arbitrary Power lodged in them, without a cauſe of Miſdemeanor, or of incapacity particularly aſſigned &amp; repreſented to the King himſelf, whoſe gifts, that are properly and Legally in his diſpoſall, cannot be taken away by any ſubordinate Power, without his conſent Firſt had and obtained in the matter. But yet I grant, that now after the deceaſe of that incomparable Prince, and the Reſtitution of the Charter, all the Truſts that were Former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly lodged in the City do naturally return together with it, and that the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Viſitation of this Hoſpitall is in them, unleſs the King and Queen ſhall pleaſe to interpoſe, which they may by Law do as often as they think Fit, and take the Juriſdiction in General or the ordering of any particular matter or affair into their own hands, but yet ſtill it continues good, that that which was Legally Eſtabliſh'd by a Lawfull and rightfull King, cannot, and ought not to be changed or altered by any Subordinate Power or Authority what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, without a Cauſe aſſigned, without a Grievance prov'd, without a fault alledg'd, in the Perſon that is intended to be diſplac'd, becauſe this is not ſo much to claim a Juriſdiction over A. or B. to whom I grant as Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernors, they are Superiour, but to Challenge and Arrogate a Power to themſelves Superior to that, From which alone they derive it, and that is From the King, which all Men muſt needs ſee to be impoſſible &amp; abſurd. Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther let any man here object that we were placed here by the Kings Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſioners not by the King himſelf, and that the Commiſſion was Arbitrary and Illegall. For Firſt, it is a Maxim in Law and reaſon, <hi>quod quis facit per alium Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cit
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95499:5"/> per<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe,</hi> what the King does by his Commiſſioners he does by himſelf, and though I will not meddle with the Legality of the proceeding in the avoid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Charter, and entring up Judgment againſt it, yet thus much I will ſay, that the Charter, whether right or wrong, being Actually voided, there was no way left to manage the Affairs of the City but by Commiſſion from the King, and that what is neceſſary in the preſent Circumſtances for the quiet and peaceable Adminiſtration of ſo Populous a City, may be ſaid at leaſt to have Secondary Lawfnllneſs, a Lawfullneſs deriving and holding from that neceſſity, though that which gave occaſion to it, ſhould be al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and admitted to be Illegall, a Controverſy with which I have nothing to do, &amp; which I do not pretend to underſtand; but as for that part of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion which concern'd the Hoſpital, it was in Vertue of a Power, which was always veſted in the King, and which he might always delegate to whom he pleaſed, ſo that all the Acts they did in this affair, were unqueſtionably va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid and Lawfull in themſelves, and cannot be cancell'd or evacuated by any leſs Authority, without a reaſon of Equity, or an Emergent reaſon of neceſſity aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiign'd. Suppoſe the King and Queen ſhould graciouſly commit to the Mayor, Aldermen, and Commonalty of the City, the care and management of the To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer of <hi>London,</hi> and the diſpoſall of the Places of Conſtable and Lieutenant, and Maſter of the Ordinance <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they ſhall ſtill be preſumed notwithſtanding this, to reſerve a Power of Viſitation to themſelves, it is reſerved in the nature of the truſt, though it were not expreſsly and poſitively provided for, and ſo it is here, the Kings Charity is as much and as naturally in his own diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall whenever he pleaſeth to concern himſelf about it, as his Arſenalls or Maga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zins, and, indeed the difference between theſe two is no more, then that by the one the King provides for the Safety and defence of his Subjects, and by the other he relieves the neceſſities of thoſe by an effect of his mercy, whom all his power cannot defend againſt the wants and Infirmities that are and will be always incident to humane Nature, and it is but fit he ſhould be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy'd, whenever he deſires it, as to the Conduct and management of one of theſe truſts, as well as of the Other. If the King notwithſtanding ſuch Commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, ſhould after Enquiry and Viſitation made, diſplace the reſpective Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers in the Tower, and put others in their ſtead, there is no man living, I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve, in this caſe that will pretend to diſpute his unqueſtionable right in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it, neither would it be Lawfull to diſplace them without his conſent, though in all other matters, and in all Future Elections when a Vacancy ſhall happen, the Commiſſion ſhould ſtill continue &amp; the powers to act under it re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main entire as before, but their Commiſſion cannot extend to things already determin'd by the King, becauſe the Kings authority is the Fountain of their power; and to reverſe his determination without a reaſon of equity or neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, is to diſown that authority under which they act, and by conſequence to diſannull their own, for rivers muſt be dry when the Fountain is deſtroyed.</p>
               <p>If a man be Tenant to a Landlord and have a leaſe under him, he perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Covenants that are ſtipulated between them, he cannot be ejected out of his Farm, or deprived of his Tenant-right, which is a ſort of ſecondary Frcehold, ſo that he may renew his leaſe from time to time, and ought to be conſidered <hi>caeteris paribus,</hi> beyond any other pretender, this being a kind of Charter-Office under the Lord of the Fee, but if a man take a Servant with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any other condition then that of paying him wages for his ſervice, he may part with him at pleaſure for a good reaſon or for none at all, for the law does
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:95499:6"/> not tell us who ſhall be are ſervants, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> or oblige us to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ep them who her we will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>honi which were in ſome ſenſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>, and I to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> order of Government <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of things, but we may k<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> whom we pleaſe; and as long as we pleaſe, and diſmiſs them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> humour as well as for a reaſon. If therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e in this Hoſpitall are Servants to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Maſter, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving wages and Salaries for our work, which Maſter is firſt of all the King, and Secondly a Corporation entruſted by and under him, there is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> queſtion but that the King in whom the firſt power is lodged, may eject <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or Mr. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> at his pleaſure, and we cannot complain of any legall wrong. neither can we renew any pretentions for the future, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> of a legall right, we never having had any other ſort of right then what was or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary and dependent upon his will; but a Corporation acting under him, though the generall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be actually <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> upon them, yet they cannot diſplace a particular perſon whom the King hath choſen, with out firſt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting to his Majeſty the reaſons of it in order to the obtaining his conſent, ſo long as he is alive. For a deputy &amp; a ſervant can do no legall act in oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition to the principall from whom the power is derived, but they may and ought to repreſent their reaſons, if they be of conſequence to the good of the houſe, and if he will not Dear them, they have diſcharged their duty, and ought to be content with the honour and ſatisfaction of having endeavour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> to do juſtice, and of having eaſed their conſciences of the guilt that would have lain upon them, by a willfull neglect of the truſt committed, to them, and after his deceaſe, as it is in our caſe, only the Succeſſor can deſtroy, what the Predeceſſor hath done out of the fullneſs and plenitude of his power, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as impoſſible for a leſſer power to deſtroy the act of a greater, as it is for a private man by virtue of any private authority and right, which he may aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume or fancy to himſelf, to chuſe whether he will obey an act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment that concerns him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> with by another act, of equall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority in its legiſlative originall, and of greater in its poſt liminious applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, becauſe it ſupercedes the obedience to the other, and for any leſſe power without a reaſon given or an application made to the Sovereign then in being, to reverſe what the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> by his own rightfull power hath ordained, is for ſervants to aſſume that diſpenſing power to themſelves, which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cry ſo loudly and ſo deſprvedly in their Maſters, for there is no right in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but legall right, and for any that have not authority, to reverſe the legal act of a ſuperiour power, muſt needs be inauthoritative, illegall, and void.</p>
               <p>If this argument which I deſign only to juſtify my ſelf, and to ſhew upon what bottom my title to the place of Hoſpitaller ſtands, does in its applicati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on prove too much, and extend it ſelf to others as well as my ſelf, thoſe Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen that claim and are actually repoſſeſſed upon the reſtitution of the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, may thank themſelves for ſolliciting Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> to come up and renew his crackt and illegall pretentions, and for making this defence, which I would have been very glad to have let alone, to become as neceſſary with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect to me, as is is juſt and honeſt in it ſelf.</p>
               <p>If the Right Honourable the Lord Mayor, and the Honourable Court of Aldermen, to whom I pay all that deference and reſpect which their great quality and Character Juſtly calls for, ſhall look upon this as written in derogation to them, and to the power and truſt committed to their Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court, I humbly hope. when they have duely conſiders of the matter, they will concurr with me, and that if I ſhould maintain the contrary
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:95499:6"/> poſition they would think themſelves concerned out of a principle of Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and duty to eject me out of this houſe, that it is by no means a d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minution to their juſt Rights, in thoſe things which the Sovereig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath not determined, to acknowledge his Legall Sovereignty in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> which he hath, For the King acted in the Regulation of this Houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Virtue of any Arbitrary Power, which he unjuſtly aſſumed and arrogat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to himſelf, but by ſuch an one, as is inherent in him, by the reſerve in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Charter of the Royal Founder, by Act of Parliament, and by the very N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and reaſon of the thing, by which he muſt always be ſuppoſed to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted with a Power, to ſee that his own Charities be rightly diſpoſed. The King is the Firſt Viſitor of this <hi>Hoſtell de die<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>,</hi> this Houſe of <hi>Invalids,</hi> the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen are the Second, acting by a Power deriva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive from him, and therefore it is plain they cannot reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ind an Act of his, which would have been Legall in it ſelf, becauſe all Legall Acts done and paſſed by a Legall Superior Power, cannot be reſcinded without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of the Sovereign, by any Subordinate Authority acting under it, becauſe this were to rob and deprive him of that Supremacy and to aſſert his Prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gative to themſelves, and if that grave and wiſe Aſſembly in this hurry of Affairs have yielded a little too far to the Sollicitations and Importunities of Men without a Title, and proceeding upon a falſe &amp; Erroneous Hypotheſis of the Reſtitution of the Charter, which hath no manner of connexion with our Caſe, yet a <hi>Facto ad jus Conſequeutia non valet,</hi> the Fact and the right are two things, and the Judgment of that right, in what Perſons it is placed, we humbly conceive with all imaginable ſubmiſſion to the Court of Aldermen, lyes unqueſtionably before the King, whoſe juſt Power in this or any other matter, I hope it will never be a crime to maintain. For as one Act of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot be repealed but by the Act of another, ſo the Act of a King in thoſe Affairs wherein he hath a proper cognizance and Legall Power can only be reſcinded by himſelf or his Succeſſor in the Imperial Seat, unleſs they be ſuch Acts as are Limited by time, as in the affair of Parents or Temporary Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations or the like; and then at the expiration of that term they die, and are repealed of themſelves; ſo that having been placed in this Station by one King and allowed by another, I truſt his preſent Majeſty ſhall have no oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion to think any otherwiſe then Favourably concerning me, and I rely up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Grace and Goodneſs of King <hi>William</hi> and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> that the Gift of Gods Viccgerents will ſtill be without repentance, as well is thoſe of the Divinity it ſelf.</p>
               <p>That I appeal to the Throne, it is becauſe I ſee the whole affair lying ſo naturally proſtrate at the Footſtool, and that the Judgment of it cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertain to any other Court or Judicature whatſoever, till it be remitted from thence, and I ſhall very willingly acquieſce in the Determination of that Power, in whomſoever it is lodged, (is being too little an Imployment for the thoughts of Princes that have ſo vaſt objects to exerciſe themſelves upon) to whomſoever the Sovereign ſhall pleaſe to referr it, but more eſpecially I re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe an entire confidence, a Fixt, unſhaken, and I had almoſt ſaid; a demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrative aſſurance, in the Favour of that Honourable Court to which the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary inſpection and Viſitation of this houſe belongs, being in ſome ſenſe an Orphan of the City, left deſtitute by a good, but an unfortunate Parent, that was undone in part by the Fatall Conflagration, and in part by other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidents incident to Trade. I have a great deal of reaſon to expect from ſuch
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95499:7"/> a Conſtitution, where the Lord Mayor, next under his Majeſty whom God preſerve, is my Political Father, the Aldermen my Guardians, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons all allyed to me in the Quality of Brethren, I ſay, I have a great deal of reaſon to expect and I do with great aſſurance wait for it, that I ſhall not only have ſtrict Juſtice done me, if my cauſe come to be determin'd at that Barr, but that I ſhall have all the Favour that Equity will afford me, and ſuch an Equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that is mixt with ſomething of affection to a ſhrubb of their own growth, that calls for no raines, no dewes but what are Naturall and Hereditary to it, for water and Refreſhment.</p>
               <p>I know no perſon in the Court of Aldermen, whom upon this account at leaſt, I have not reaſon to believe my friend, unleſs it be one Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, Sr <hi>Patiente Ward</hi> I mean, before whom when I preached, when he was Lord Mayor of this City, I had the misfortune to leave him out of my pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er before Sermon, for that it was an involuntary thing, ariſing from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſigning negligence, without any ill intention, I call the great God of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven and Earth to witneſs, and this is no more then what I have affirmed a thouſand times in the company of my friends, when I had no intereſt to perſwade me not to own it, if the affront that was ſuſpected, had been re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all on my part, and it is further obſervable that I did not only omit him, but the Aldermen, Sheriffs, and Commonalty too, who are all of them prayed for upon theſe occaſions; now there is no man in his wits but muſt ſuppoſe me to have been quite out of them, if I had deſign'd a Publick affront to ſo Venerable an Aſſembly, ſo Illuſtrious a Bench, ſo great and po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulous a City, in which I had not only received my Nativity, and a great part of my Education, but in which I had at that time among all ranks, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny favourers, Godſpeeders and friends, and if after this any ſuſpicion can remain upon the mind of that Gentleman, that it was deſignedly done, which to me it ſeems impoſſible that it ſhould, then I humbly intreat him if no other conſideration will prevail with him, to let the memory and old friendſhip of my deceaſed <hi>Father,</hi> intercede with him for my for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giveneſs.</p>
               <p>But if it be as I have repreſented, that the true and only legall deciſion of the controverſy between Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and me lies ſolely and entirely in the Kings breaſt, unleſs he ſhall pleaſe to put it into ſome other hands; Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> knows who it is that preached a famous Sermon at <hi>Abingdon</hi> Aſſizes upon a moſt infamous ſubject, the juſtification of the worſt of parricides, of the Execrable Murther of that glorious <hi>Martyr,</hi> who fell a Sacrifice to the Church of <hi>England</hi> and the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Religion. He juſtifyed and gloried in that horrid Fact when many of the pretended Judges themſelves had repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he Crucify'd the Royall Saint afreſh and put him to an open ſhame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore a numerous aſſembly, and in the face of juſtice it ſelf, when others were waſhing off that bloud with their tears, and would have been glad with the expence of their own lives to have retrieved the ineſtimable loſs of his, which brought ſo black a guilt, and was followed by ſo miſerable uſurpation and confuſion. Now what favour can Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> expect from the Royall Grandſon of that Martyred Prince, when the principles of that Sermon are levell'd at himſelf and at all Succeeding Princes whatſoever, when Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> and his Partizans are angry: though there be no good Subject but hath ever maintain'd that the Perſons of Princes are unqueſtionably ſacred, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the reall and groſs exerciſe of Arbitrary Power, whatever becomes of their
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95499:7"/> Politicall capacity and Regall adminiſtration. Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> may think it plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant to waſh his impure hands in Royall bloud, but that was not that waſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which the Prophet <hi>David</hi> required in all that miniſter in the holy things. <hi>I will waſh my hands in Innocence,</hi> ſaid he, <hi>and ſo will I go to thine Altar.</hi> It is true the act of oblivion pardons this crime, but to pardon and to forget are two things, to pardon and to reward are two more: if <hi>Salmoſius</hi> would have accepted of ſo ſmall a pittance, as the place of Hoſpitaller of <hi>St. Tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas Southwark,</hi> he would have become the place and title very well, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was very ſuitable for him, to eat the Kings bread who had defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his cauſe, but <hi>Milton</hi> would certainly have been an awkward man in that ſtation, and what is Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> I pray better then he? unleſs, it be that Mr. <hi>Milton</hi> underſtood reaſon, argument and wit, if he would but have em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed thoſe-talents to better purpoſe, which Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> does not; but that Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> is more malicious, black and <hi>Saturnine</hi> in his Sermon, then Mr. <hi>Milton</hi> in his book, and that the one is more dull and Phlegmatique then the other. <hi>John Goodwin</hi> a man of much more honeſty and ſenſe then Mr. <hi>H.</hi> being ſo far carried away by the Republican bigotry of thoſe unhappy times, which overflowed and bore-down Loyallty with a rapid and reſiſtleſs torrent, was content with his pardon and leave of retirement into a private corner, without perking up impudently for preferments and rewards, when he had ſo juſtly forfieted his life; and the ſame was Mr. <hi>Milton's</hi> caſe, who en deavoured to make ſome ſort of attonement for his crime in the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Hiſtory which he after Publiſh'd, by offering up a devout ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of praiſe and admiration to the memory of that excellent and incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable King, and giving him that great and lofty Character which he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved: but what hath Mr. <hi>H.</hi> ever done to make amends for his fault? what inſtance can he produce of his ſorrow &amp; repentance? And yet ſo foul a crime ſo publiquely committed, a preaching and a printed crime, can never be ſaid to be truly repented of without a preaching and printed fatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for otherwiſe though there may be ſome inward compunction &amp; remorſe, yet the ſatisfaction &amp; the injury are to hold ſome ſort of proportion with each other, and to do a publique, a notorious crime, without a repentance and ſatisfaction equall to it, does not come up to the nature of true repentance, but it is like robbing our Brother of a Pound and paying him a Penny by way of Reſtitution, which is but to continue in the Robbery ſtill, and ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to own and juſtify the fact, then to condemn and diſapprove it.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can farther inform us if he pleaſeth, who it was that vext and perſecuted his neighbour for teaching a School without a licence, and yet had no licenſe for himſelf at the ſame time, but anſwer'd to the name of <hi>Thomas</hi> inſtead of <hi>William</hi> to ſave his Bacon at a Viſitation, and he can tell us further of the ſelf-ſame perſon, how he ſtood engaged by promiſe for the payment of a ſum of money, and yet refuſed it after ſeaven years time, under the protection of the ſtatute of limitation, and many other things Mr. <hi>H.</hi> can tell of that man, when he hath a mind to furniſh a <hi>Biographer</hi> with mate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rials for the life of fo matchleſs a worthy, and if this man ſhould happen to be the ſame with the t'other, I doubt me he hath not yet repented of his Treaſon, for this is treaſon too; it is treaſon againſt humane Society, which ſuch prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples and ſuch practices would certainly deſtroy, and this is the very foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of Treaſon againſt Princes, whoſe Perſons are ſo Sacred above all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, not ſo much upon their own private account, as for the ſake of
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95499:8"/> the publique, which is highly concern'd &amp; intereſted in their ſafety, and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in all the injuries they receive, and thus much may ſuffice for the Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter of <hi>Hugonides</hi> and his Freind, whom I would not have treated at ſo rough a rate, but that they have turn'd raillery into a pertinent thing, and made it ſo abſolutely neceſſary for me to expoſe them, that it may appear at leaſt there is no merit of congruity betwixt my ſmall preferment and them.</p>
               <p>What hath been ſaid hitherto, hath been upon occaſion of the Stating of the Caſe, as it was repreſented to Three worthy Gentlemen, learned in the Law, in order to obtaining their Opinions upon it, I come now very briefly to ſay ſomething with relation to the Opinions themſelves, by all which it is agreed that the ordinary Power of Viſitation and inſpection into the affairs and Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers of this Houſe is in the Governors for the time being, that is to ſay, Firſt in the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen, and Secondly thoſe other Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and Citizens that are deputed by them or allowed by their permiſſion to manage and Tranſact the Hoſpitall Affairs, and that the reſpective Officers belonging to it, are not Charter Officers that have a fixt Intereſt and a ſetled right, but only Servants at pleaſure receiving wages for their work, and to be diſmiſt at diſcretion, when the Governors think fit, though behaving themſelves well in their ſeverall Employments, they may be ſaid to have an Equitable right, and that it would be an Hardſhip in the Governors, which they could not juſtify to themſelves, to turn them off againſt their wills in ſuch Circumſtances as theſe, but however theſe Opinions do at leaſt ſay thus much for us, that the Perſons claiming againſt us have no Legall right, and that there is no neceſſary Connexion betwixt the Regulation of the Hoſpitall and the Reſtitution of the Charter, ſo that Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> is very much out of the way, when he inſiſts ſo unskillfully upon a Legall right, and proves himſelf to be as bad a Lawyer, as he is a Divine or a man.</p>
               <p>But yet I confeſs there is one thing in the opinion of that great and Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Perſon Mr <hi>Sergeant Pemberion,</hi> which I cannot perfectly aſſent to, though I ſhould not preſume to own a difference in matters of this nature from a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon ſo profoundly Learned in his Profeſſion, but that the Succeſs of our cauſe does in ſome meaſure depend upon it, he is pleaſed to ſay that upon the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the Charter, and the avoidance of that Commiſſion that ſupply'd its place, there were no Governors left either old, or new, but that it was perfectly at the diſcretion of the Court of Aldermen to regulate and order all thoſe matters as they pleaſed; but in an humble Oppoſition to this, I preſume to offer, that the King being at all times veſted with a Power of Viſiting the Hoſpitalls and of making from time to time ſuch Regulations in them as to his Princely Wiſdom ſhall ſeem moſt meet and Expedient, though the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion be diſſolved, yet the Regall Power and Authority ſtill remains, and what a King hath done by vertue of his Legall, and rightfull Power, always inherent and veſted in his Perſon, that nothing leſs them a King can deſtroy, ſo that thoſe new Governors being a Conſtitutive and Eſſentiall part of this very Regulation, they muſt ſtand Independent from the Court of Aldermen, till the King declare them to have nothing to do in this Houſe, and the old ones that were Ejected, whether Officers or Governors cannot be readmitted without the Kings conſent, the Kings Authority and the Validity of it in all thoſe Acts to which it extends it ſelf, being always the ſame, though indiffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Perſons that are inveſted with it, ſo that in all the Legall Juriſdictions of a King, it is <hi>ille aperit &amp; nemo claudit,</hi> he openeth and no man ſhuts, he ſhuts
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95499:8"/> and no man opens, nothing but a King can diſſolve thoſe Obligations or an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>null thoſe Rights which a Lawfull King hath Eſtabliſht. And indeed it were a great incongruity in the King, very unbecoming either his wiſdom or greatneſs, and a great diminution to his power, if he ſhould erect and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute a Commiſſion to regulate abuſes, in ſuch things as do naturally and le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gally belong to his viſitation and inſpection, and yet when the Commiſſion was diſolved, the regulation ſhould ceaſe, which would be to as little pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, as if no ſuch regulation had ever been made, only it would reflect a diſparagement upon the King as weak and inconſiderable, and pretending to more power then really he had, for that regulation which is actually diſſolved, after the diſſolution of that Commiſſion by which it was made, muſt needs have been unjuſt and unlawfull before it, for lawfull and juſt things will-endure. Nay, I appeal to all the world, what confuſion it would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduce into the affairs of the City, if all the acts of the Commiſſioners for the ſpace of five years together, ſhould by the expiration or diſſolution of the Commiſſion be rendered null and void, though yet upon ſuppoſition that the Charter could not be voided, which I do not concern my ſelf whether it could or no, the Commiſſion was ſo far illegall, if we look down to it's root, though its neceſſity may perhaps plead ſomething in its excuſe, as I have hinted before; but as for that branch of the Commiſſion which concerned the Hoſpitalls, it was as I have ſhewn, ſtrictly legall, and therefore all thoſe acts which paſs'd under and from it, of which the election of Governours and Officers were two, muſt need be legall and conſequently valid. No Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> do not pleaſe and flatter your little ſelf with vain imaginations, the regulation is as valid, as the firſt authority from whence it ſprang, and that is the Kings, though the Commiſſion that managed and ordered that whole matter be now actually diſſolved, and I think I have given ſo very good reaſon for it that even your own impudence, that face of yours which is your un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſtionable Property, and is peculiar to your ſelf, cannot without ſome ſmall diſcolouring, ſome ſtreaks and Eſſays towards the Modeſty of a bluſh, oppoſe it any longer.</p>
               <p>But yet I grant, that though the Governors do manifeſtly hold by a Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>or Tenure, to any that the Court of Aldermen can give them, yet the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter being reſtored, the Ordinary Viſitation and Inſpection of the Hoſpitall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns together with it, and the Aldermen in the Courſe of things and in the Right and Power of Adminiſtration being Superior to the Commons of the City, and much more to any among the Governors that are not Free of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, they may ſo tye up the hands of the Subordinate Powers, as that they ſhall have no right to any thing but their Green S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aves, and cannot move one ſtep in any Emergent bus'neſs of the Houſe without the direction of the Court of Aldermen or at leaſt their tacit conſent, ſo that I confeſs the Aldermen have Fully retrived the exerciſe of all their Power, in all Emergencies that ſhall happen <hi>de futuro,</hi> and in all matters which the King hath not determin'd, and which none but the King can Evacuate or diſanull, and have left the others little or nothing, but the Stile and Title of Governors, of which I conceive they cannot be diveſted without the Kings expreſs, or at leaſt implicit con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>currence by referring the whole matter to the Honourable Bench, but for us that are Officers, it is a little otherwiſe; it is true we are at his Majeſties diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſal, as well as the others, but only that during his Majeſties pleaſure, we know our reſpective Places and our Stations, and are obliged to act in our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:95499:9"/> reſpective Spheres; otherwiſe the buſineſs of the houſe muſt be at a ſtand, and by conſequence the Royall Charity be diſappointed, and this is true likewiſe as to our Maſters themſelves, as to ſome particular Acts, that is, of taking in the Sick, and diſmiſſing the Sound or the Incurable and auditing the Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, but only they can make no new order as a Court, without the Expreſs or at leaſt the tacit and implicit conſent of the Court of Aldermen. It is no derogation to that great and wiſe Court to ſay that the King is their Superior, not only in Generall in his Tranſcendent Dignity and Power, but more par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly in all thoſe matters which belong naturally and Legally to his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpection and care, though by the Charter of his Royall Predeceſſor, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary adminiſtration of that very Province be committed to them. For this I am ſure there is none of them but will very readily grant and Zealouſly aſſert, that the King is their unqueſtionable Superior in all Lawfull matters, and that the King of <hi>England</hi> never dyes, but is always the ſame, &amp; we do very wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly acknowledge that by the Reſtitution of the Charter, their old Authority returns together with it, only that that Authority hath now a Partiall and a Temporary reſtraint upon it, by the King, (who is the Fountain of that Power by which they Act,) his having already determin'd the Rights and Stations of ſome particular perſons, and we ſay we are legally poſſeſſed of our reſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive places, till we are legally ejected, that is, till it be done by an equall au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to that which put us in, or till the King pleaſe to determine other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe concerning us, either expreſſely or by returning back to the Court of Aldermen the entire ordinary power of viſitation, which it doth not appear to me that he hath yer done, in things that by the Royall authority have been already determined and ought to ſtand firm till they be annull'd by the ſame: and I do not ſpeak this, neither would I be ſo underſtood, as if I were a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of the Judgment of that Honourable Court, for I know their Juſtice, their Goodneſs, their Integrity and Candour, and am not afraid to throw my ſelf upon it, but I have ſaid this for no other reaſon, but that in my ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion, upon the beſt and moſt impartiall judgment I can make of things, it is the true ſtate of the Caſe, and I hope his Majeſty will not be offended with me for having thus largely vindicated his Royall rights, though in an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of greater conſequence to us his poor Suppliants and Servants then himſelf, and I entreat the Right-Honourable the Lord Mayor and the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable Court of Aldermen to conſider, that it is not we that encroach up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their rights or pretend to diſpute their lawfull jurisdiction, but it is they who upon grounds which they cannot juſtify, would ſupplant us, for they pretend a legall Claim upon the reſtitution of the Charter, which is to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>own the ordinary Jurisdiction and to put themſelves out of the diſcretion of the Court, upon a bottom of legall property, which they have not, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as we do not diſown it upon any other account, then only upon an Emergent point of Law, particular to the circumſtances we are in, in which the Kings honour and prerogative are concerned.</p>
               <p>It remains now only that I conſider as clearly as I can, the circumſtances peculiar betwixt Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> and me, as to the right or equity of our Caſe, and I think in generall it is already proved, ſuppoſing Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> to have had a legall choice, when he firſt made his entrance upon this little preferment, yet that he was legally Ejected, that is, Ejected by virtue of that Authority-Royall, which hath reſerved to it ſelf in the very Charter and Conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelf (beſides other reaſons that do naturally ſuppoſe and juſtify ſuch a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:95499:9"/> of viſiting and inſpecting the affairs of this houſe, with a <hi>non obſtante</hi> to all former orders of any inferiour and delegated power concerning them, and if theſe two authorities may mutually reverſe what either of them hath at any time ordained, then Superiority and Subjection does manifeſtly looſe their nature; and there is nothing but diſorder and confuſion ſucceeding in their ſtead, for no Government can ſtand in any place whatſoever, where there are two contrary Authorities diſſolving one another, and reſcinding each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Conſtitutions and Decrees. <hi>Mr. Hughes</hi> being therefore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ejected by the King, and I by the ſame Authority put into his place, does in vain inſiſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Illegality of my choice, or upon the Firmneſs and validity of his own, unleſs he can ſhew an Authority Superiour to that by which he was ejected and I choſen, which was done, as he knows very well, by the Supreme Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary and Viſitor of this houſe, or unleſs he can give a reaſon why a Maſter of an houſe may not act with his ſervants after an arbitrary and unaccountable manner, ſo far as the retaining them in his houſe &amp; ſervice, or the dimiſſing of them from it is concerned, and ſince he cannot ſay any thing to the diminution of one King, eſpecially in a matter of inconteſtable right, which does not equal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſtrike at the unqueſtionable right and prerogative of another, he will do well to tread gingerly upon ſo tender a point, and to ſpeak very ſoftly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning it, and yet when he hath done and ſaid the moſt he can, the Hoſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall though they may poſſibly pretend to be exempt from Epiſcopall Jurisdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and if they had not pretended to thus much at leaſt, Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> had ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come thither, yet they will never I hope, be exempted from the Kings, and will not only remain to be a reall, though lame and imperfect part of his Dominions, but alſo the object of his peculiar care; who is in generall the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his Countrey, but more eſpecially the refuge of the Infirm and Weak.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Ruſtat</hi> whoſe Exemplary bounty and Munificence founded thoſe Scholarſhips that are called by his name in the Floriſhing Society of <hi>Jeſus</hi> Colledge in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> reſerved to himſelf during his own life time, the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of ſuch as ſhould be choſen into them, and it would have been ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hard to deny him, though he had not claimed it, a Prerogative ſo natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and ſo juſt as this, much more would this have been ungratefull and diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyall in Subjects to their King, during the whole Reign of <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>6th,</hi> after the Foundation and Endowment of this Houſe, to deny him a right of Enquiring from one time to another into the management of ſo great a truſt, though no reſervation in his Charter had been made, which reſervation muſt for that reaſon more eſpecially reſpect his Succeſſors then himſelf, who had an undoubted and unqueſtionable right of Inſpecting and inquiring into that Royall Charity which was ſo ſtrictly and ſo immediately his own; it was I ſay, a reſervation to his Succeſſors rather then to him, which gives them a right of Law, (beſides a right of Congruity which they will always have in the Donations of their Predeceſſors, to ſee that their Piety and Charity be not abuſed) to examine or inquire into the management of this Truſt, and to confirm or alter, what is already Eſtabliſht by a Subordinate Power, as to their Princely Wiſdom ſhall ſeem meet, and when Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> or any of his Friends, can clear themſelves handſomely of this one conſideration, which ſtabs his whole claim, and goes to the heart of his cauſe, then I will yield to him without any more ado, though I have ſeveral other material things to ſuggeſt in bar to his pretences, which are ſo unſound and rotten in every Point and Circumſtance, that no man ever appeared to lay his claim to any
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95499:10"/> thing with greater diſadvantage then Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> hath done.</p>
               <p>For firſt it is notorious that when he was firſt admitted into this place and for about three years after he never was Epiſcopally ordained, as the Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the ſeverall Acts of Uniformity, but more eſpecially that which is called the <hi>Bartholomew</hi> Act, do unavoidably require, nothing of that Act being ever yet repealed that I know of, unleſs it be that Clauſe which concerned the Solemn League and Covenant, which was intended to be only a Temporary thing and was to expire of it ſelf after a certain term of years, which is now long ſince Elapſed. He ſays he was cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen into this Houſe by Fourſcore Governors, and to do him a kindneſs it ſhall be if he pleaſeth, four thouſand, For let them be never ſo many, it was in it ſelf a void Act, For they could not chuſe a Non-Conformiſt to be Chaplain here, to eat at the Kings coſt in the Kings Houſe, who is the Protector and Guardian of the Laws, and to be maintain'd by way of Salary under the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an Eccleſiaſticall Perſon out of the Publick Revenues of the State, as if Non-Conformity were to be encouraged out of the Publick Revenue, at the ſame time when it was ſo ſeverely and expreſsly forbidden by the Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute Laws of the Kingdom, ſeveral times reiterated and repeated.</p>
               <p>I do not ſpeak this out of any want of Tenderneſs to a Religious diſſent, For God Forbid but every man ſhould Act according to his Conſcience, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther did I ever oppoſe any diſſenting Party, ſo as to think them in Juſtice puniſhable for their diſſent, out of any other Principle then what was meerly Political, for the Preſervation of the Publick Peace, which is the certain and undoubted meaſure upon which the Acts of Parliament in that behalf have proceeded, and if I have any where ſaid any thing with heat or with contempt of Separatiſts and Diſſenters, out of too much precipitance in writing, or out of the raſhneſs and inadvertency which is incident to Youth, yet it was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways my Principle, that all Mankind by nature are Endowed with all that Liberty of Action, of Opinion and Enjoyment, which is conſiſtent with pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate peace and reſt, on with the Safety and Tranquillity of the Publique, which in a Society or body Politique is that which is moſt eſpecially to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded, and that the Legall reſtraints are only Artificial things ſuperinduced by neceſſity, experience and length of time, to promote the advantage of a Nation, by making proviſion for its Peace, Ornament, Plenty and Protection, or to prevent its ruine by reſtraining and curbing thoſe interferring paſſions that have a Naturall Tendency to ſo bad an End; No man can complain of me that ever I Perſecuted him for his Conſcience ſake, but ſome that have been actually under the Hatches of the Law, I have endeavoured to relieve and bring off as well as I could, as the Perſons, if they be living, whoſe names I have now forgot, may remember; I never pronounced an Excommnication in my life, and am naturally very tender in a matter of ſuch dreadfull conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence as that is, but an Abſolution from it, I have with great Chearfullneſs and Alacrity recited; there is nothing in the whole world that hath afforded me greater trouble and diſſatisfaction of mind, then to ſee the Frailty, Folly, and perverſeneſs of humane nature to be ſuch, that we muſt needs be Falling out and Squabbling about opinions, which may be United in Charity, though never ſo oppoſite or diſtant in themſelves, and which are by no means incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petible or inconſiſtent with our common happineſs and Salvation; but yet I have always been and I am ſtill in my own thoughts a profeſt Enemy to an unlimited Toleration, though the Naturall tenderneſs and compaſſion of my
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95499:10"/> Temper, to which even Juſtice hath a Cruell and Frightfull appearance, will never ſuffer me to vex my Neighbour upon a Religious account; my reaſon why I am againſt it, is, becauſe long experience hath Taught and inculcated a Lamentable truth, that men will always be Embroiling the Peace of their Country upon Religious pretences, that there is a mixture of paſſion, a leaven of deſign, a ſecret root of Ambition or Revenge, that frequently lies hid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſanctify'd appearance, and that it is not ſo much Salvation in the other World or truth in this, as power that is aimed at and contended for; and if theſe inconveniences could any way be prevented without the rigours and ſeverities of humane Laws, I for my part ſhould think it the blackeſt Tyranny in the World, that the Liberty of thought and of opinion, or the freedom of a pleaſant and diverting Converſation (that ought in reaſon to be the reſult of ſuch differences as theſe, by mens comparing their Sentiments together) which are the firſt, moſt Naturall, moſt Eſſentiall and deeply rooted Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of mankind, ſo long as they keep within the bounds of modeſty and Friendſhip, ſhould be Fettered and Entangled by poſitive Conſtitutions, which is the true Spirit and Myſtery of the Papacy it ſelf, and is the greateſt enemy that can be to that curious &amp; inquiſitive temper, that Philoſophicall <hi>Geni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us,</hi> that ſoaring &amp; ſearching diſpoſition of our minds, in which the true perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction &amp; dignity of humane nature conſiſts, and if any expedient of comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion can be found, that ſhall upon experiment prove ſucceſsfull to the recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciling thoſe Feuds and Animoſities which we labour under, by making the paſſage into our Church ſo much more wide and ſpatious then it was before, that weak, but conſcientious men may enter in without the danger of being Crowded or hurt, if any way can be contrived that Liberty may be granted without injury to the Publique, even to thoſe who will ſtill ſeparate after the largeſt Conceſſions, there is no perſon living that would more ſincerely rejoyce, to ſee that puniſhment was rendered an uſeleſs and unneceſſary thing, by Charities being ſubſtituted in the place of Juſtice, and all thoſe breaches made up by a Practicall agreement, which it is impracticable and impoſſible ever to reconcile, by a concord of thought, or a Symphathetique harmony of opinion, but this though I could wiſh to ſee with all my heart, yet I muſt needs ſay I never can expect it, and therefore all that can be reaſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ably done in ſuch a caſe, is to make the Termes of Communion ſo large, which I am glad to ſee doing by the Wiſdom and Prudence of this preſent Parliament, as that great numbers of Honeſt and good men, who cannot get rid of their prejudices and miſtakes may be added to the Church, taking care all the while, which I doubt not but ſuch a wiſe Aſſembly will effectually do, that we do not pull down the Church under pretence of Enlarging it, for a Vineyard is always ſuppoſed to have its Fences, and a Church that has no Walls or Hedges to defend it is ſo farr from being a Chriſtian Society, that it is indeed no Society at all, and is rather to be called a common Field then a <hi>Catholique</hi> Church or a Garden full of Spices which the Lord hath bleſſed.</p>
               <p>It is not therefore Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his diſſent from the Eſtabliſh'd worſhip, when he took upon him firſt to be Chaplain of this place, that I reprove or find fault with, but that he only waſhed the outſide of the Cup and Platter, and was like thoſe Tomb-Stones which our Saviour ſpeaks of, which not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding they had an outward comelyneſs and Beauty in the ſight of thoſe that paſt by, yet within they were full of rottenneſs and dead mens bones, for what elſe but ſuch a Falſe and Phariſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>icall diſpoſition as this ſhould
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95499:11"/> make him leſs afraid of Sacriledge then of a Surplice? Of Robbery then of Common-Prayer? Of Proſtrating and Proſtituting his very Soul and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to the Unrighteous <hi>Mammon,</hi> then of bowing to the Name, and by that geſture adoring the Divinity of the Holy <hi>Jeſus?</hi> and what was it leſs then this for him to take the King's Money for diſobeying his Laws, and to receive the rewards of the State, which are pay'd and diſtributed out of the Publique Revenue, for thoſe very Actions or rather Omiſſions of his to which the Law had allotted nothing but Fines and Impriſonments and ſuch like grievous things? Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> knows very well that his Salary could not be Legally paid to him as Chaplain or <hi>Hoſpitaller</hi> of this Houſe, upon any other ſuppoſition then that of his Conformity to the Eſtabliſht Church, and to the Laws of the Land, of which the King is the Guardian and Protector, and whatever his Friends might give him as a diſſenting Preacher, which I ſhould never envy him, though it were never ſo much, Yet for him unjuſtly to rob the Church of its Patrimony, and to appropiate to himſelf, what the Law never deſigned for a Perſon ſo unquallif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ed to receive it, as he then was, how little does it differ in its nature from picking of Pockets? Or padding upon <hi>Clapham</hi> Common, or between that and <hi>London?</hi> though the Governors would have given it him, unleſs it were out of their own proper pockets, not out of the Stated and Publique Revenue of the Houſe, yet Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> ought not in Conſcience to have received it, it was in him a point of Knavery to receive, in them a breach of Truſt to give, he diſpenſed with his Conſcience and they diſpenſed with theirs, and with the Laws to boot, which it ſeems it is the clear Prerogative of Subjects to do, though at the ſame time we juſtly take it in, that our Princes ſhould not Govern themſelves and us according to them, or rather it is the peculiar Priviledge of ſome ſort of men with a <hi>non-obſtant<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to the reſt of mankind. Thoſe Fourſcore Governors he talks of, that Voted him hither, who they were I know not; neither ſhall I ever give my ſelf the Trouble to enquire, but this I am very ſure of, that this was ſo great, ſo Criminall a breach of Truſt, the greater for being committed under the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mality of a pretended Authority and Power, that from that time forward they have forfeited their Title and ought to have broken their Green Staves, as my Lord High Steward doth his white one after the Tryall of a Peer is over, and never to have pretended to the ordering or Government of this Hoſpitall any longer, for they were not ſent hither to break the Laws of the Land and of the houſe together, but to obſerve them both and to ſee that o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in their Stations do the ſame. At leaſt, thus much, I ſuppoſe, will be granted by all impartiall Men, that as Governors they had no ſuch Power, as that which they then aſſumed and arrogated to themſelves, ſo that they not being qualify'd to chuſe Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> nor Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> to be choſen by them, it was a void Act on both ſides, and where then, I beſeech you, is Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> his Title? What becomes of his claim, and his fine ſhow? When without <hi>Quo Warranto</hi>'s, Forfeitures of Charters and Commiſſions from above, the law in its own proper Channell ran ſo ſtrong againſt him, that he was Legally eje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted at the very inſtant when he was ſo Illegally choſen.</p>
               <p>Mr <hi>Hughes,</hi> I preſume, remembers what his anſwer was, when I put the queſtion to him, whether at his admiſſion into this houſe, he were in Orders or not? his Anſwer was affirmative and poſitive that he was; well pla<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>'d old <hi>Hugo,</hi> thought I to my ſelf, but Sir, ſaid I, what Orders do you mean? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> you Epiſcopally Ordained at that time? this queſtion did not pleaſe him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95499:11"/> after ſome rumbling within, as if he were troubled with winde, occaſion as I ſuppoſe, by a conteſt betwixt Intereſt and truth, the man made a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after a very wry face, which I have no words to deſcribe, to make a ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſame anſwer every whit as much diſtorted and awry as that; why truly ſaid he, I do not well remember what date my Orders do bear, which was but the ſecond part of Shuffling and Cutting; the Firſt anſwer was an Equivocation, the Second no Anſwer at all, for he knew very well that they did not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> date, till very long after his admiſſion into this place: the firſt was thought a figure peculiar to the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> but now it ſeems the Schoolmaſters have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> it too, God grant they do not teach it their boys, the Second beſides, that it was a very ſhameleſs evaſion in it ſelf, was a very mean affront and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity put upon me, as if I were ſo ſilly to ſwallow ſuch weak anſwers <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> and Subſtantiall things. Heaven help the good Gentleman and inſtruct him better by a ray of light from thence, for his noddle is as ſhallow as the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> is high, as cold and as numb'd as the grey head of <hi>Brecknock,</hi> where the ſn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> is a perpetuall Incumbent all the year, even when the Sun returning brings his <hi>Quo Warranto</hi> againſt the Winters Charter, or if two Learned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pleaſe him better, becauſe he pretends to ſomething of that ſame, let it be <hi>Rhodope</hi> and <hi>Haemus</hi> if he will, for the Top of <hi>Parnaſſus</hi> he hath nothing to do with, although he be a <hi>Paedagogue,</hi> and to that of <hi>Olympus</hi> I am ſure he will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come, unleſs he mends his manners.</p>
               <p>I know Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> urgeth in his own defence, he did it to me in a ſhort Conference which we had together, that though it is true he were incapable by Law to execute any Miniſteriall Office in this place when firſt he came to it, and for a great while after, yet at laſt he leapt into a Caſſock and a Girdle, the knot of which was a great deal. Lower then it ſhould be, and that his peaceable Enjoyment to be computed from that time to the time of his Eject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, was to be interpreted as a new choice, and is to looked upon as a tacit conſent in the Governors who made no objections, but ſuffer'd him to go on ſilently and ſmoothly in the execution of his Charge, and I am content upon one condition that this Argument ſhall paſs Muſter in his behalf, and that is, that he refund to the uſe of the Poor of this Houſe, or to the Ornament of that Chappell which he had converted into an Illegall Conventiele, all that ill gotten money, amounting in all to about 200 pounds, of which he robb'd the King, Cheated the Hoſpitall and bereft the Church, by withholding it from ſome other Perſon more capable and more deſerving, which is no more then what, I think, he is bound in ſtrict Conſcience to do, he being the firſt man I believe to be met with in Hiſtory that ever received a Publick and Stated Penſion for a Publick and continned act of Diſobedience and Contempt to the Laws of his Country, a Penſion from the King, in the Kings own Houſe, who is the Guardian and Executor of the Laws he broke. But yet ſuppoſing the connivence and ſufferance he ſpeaks of, to have ſignify'd as much as a choice, or Approbation, yet he was Legally ejected notwithſtanding this, by a Legall Authority abundantly Paramount to that Illegall and Arbitrary little Power by which he was firſt introduced into his Place, it was done by the King the Supreme Viſitor and Ordinary of this Houſe, whoſe hired Servants we all are, and may be Ejected at his pleaſure without any wrong or injuſtice, when e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver he is weary of our Service, or is diſpoſed to take other Servants in our ſtead.</p>
               <p>But I fancy I know Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his Temper ſo well that he will never con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95499:12"/> to this coſtly Propoſition, of part with ſuch a ſum of money to appeaſe a Conſcience, which is by no means ſqueamiſh, and that he would rather have ſtaid at home quietly in the Country, then have taken ſuch a trouble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome and expenſive Journey to meet with ſuch an irkſome demand, that had been made by thoſe that have Power to exact its performance; For it is plain he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived this money in the Hoſpitall's wrong and that in ſtrict Justice he is bound to Reſtitution. Wherefore ſince Mr <hi>H.</hi> will not part with his Coin, he muſt not take it ill if we ſtick cloſe to our Argument and to him, by diſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing and Proteſting againſt his tac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t conſent, for 'tis plains this Notion of a tacit conſent involves the Court of Aldermen and the King and all the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periors, as much as it did thoſe honeſt and worthy Truſtees. who broke their Truſt when they choſe him; For they did therefore only not oppoſe this choice, becauſe they knew nothing of it, they had no notice or Cogniſence of the matter, and it is as plain that neither the Court of Aldermen, nor the King would at that time have ſuffered it, had a due and particular Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of the matter been made; not the Court of Aldermen, who were all of them Members and Communicants of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and much leſs the King who would never have conſented that the Panegyriſt of Traytors, and the vile aſſertor of his Fathers Parricide, ſhould eat of his bread and live upon the fruits of his bounty, and if this did ſtill lie heavy againſt him even after his Admiſſion into Holy Orders, then the King who was the Firſt Viſitor and Inſpector of our Affairs, can never be ſuppoſed in any rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable Conſtruction to have given his Tacit conſent; ſo that in all this affair tho' we ſhould admit a tacit conſent of the Subordinate Powers, yet the Court of Aldermen and the King not concurring, it was a conſent of Deputies againſt their Principalls which is a void thing in it ſelf, and is as much as no conſent, a conſent to that which they were obliged by their truſt &amp; by their duty to their Principalls to diſallow. I ſhall not here trouble my ſelf to compute how many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fractions M. <hi>Hughes</hi> made upon the known Laws of the Land, every minute was a repeated breach For after three years that he was poſſeſt of this place, it is enough that after his Conformity to the Church, he was Guilty of very groſs and Scandalous neglects of his duty, of which I ſhall ſay more hereafter, and this is Sufficient to deſtroy his Notion of a Tacit conſent, for nothing ought to be tacitly conſented to, that cannot be explicitly and fairly defended.</p>
               <p>Mr. <hi>H.</hi> his not being in Orders for ſo long a time, his having abuſed the charity of the houſe, publickly affronted and mock'd the laws of the Land, cheated the King and interverted the publique Revenue to an illegall uſe, was reaſon enough to juſtify his expulſion from hence, notwithſtanding his halt conformity, for about a year or two before he left it, and if the King as a maſter had not had a legall arbitrary power to turn away his Servant, as every maſter hath, even without a fault, yet I hope it was a ſufficient reaſon for a Son to proceed upon, that he had juſtify'd the Murther of his Father, and it was ſtill a further aggravation that in his proper buſineſs, as a Chaplain to the houſe, after his pretended converſion to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> he was ſo groſſely neglectfull in the duties of his office, ſo that if ever Servant was legal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly turn'd away, it muſt be confeſt Mr. <hi>H.</hi> had law of his ſide when he was diſmiſt from his employment, but hath no Claime, no Shadow, no Colour, no imaginable appearance or pretence of right, for a reinveſtiture into his lapſed charge, forfieted by Sins of omiſſion and of commiſſion too, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieted for ſuch reaſons that I had almoſt ſaid, it would be a ſin and a crime
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95499:12"/> even in the ſupreme power it ſelf, which alone can legally <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> him, but by any inferibur Authority it cannot be done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and irregularity of the proceeding, without affront to the memory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bleſſed Kings, as well as injury to the affairs of the houſe, for let him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> what he will, he will ſtill be as negligent as he was before, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> bury the Dead, nor viſit the Sick, nor read prayers to the Poor, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> were ſo ſtrangely neglected and omitted by him, that it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>Clupham</hi> all the week round, and his friend Mr's <hi>Knight</hi> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ded here in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> place, and was of the two more properly to be ſtiled the Hoſpitaller <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> Thomas Southwark,</hi> ſhe managed all things in his abſence, as ſhe eaſily might, becauſe there was nothing to do, unleſs now and then a dead Corpſe to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> put into the hole, to prevent ſtanch and Annoyance to the living, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ſeems was the <hi>Sex'ton</hi> buſineſs and not his, for the ſpace of four year together, till toward the very Fag end of his time; and then by the clamours of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny but eſpecially of Mr <hi>Molins,</hi> who was then one of the <hi>Surgeons</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> houſe, he was at laſt prevail'd upon to take ſome very little care that t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> three bodies ſhould have Chriſtian buriall according to the uſage of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Church of <hi>England,</hi> whereas before the Sexton was the Curat, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Service at the Grave was, <hi>Let the dead bury the dead for William <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi>
               </p>
               <p>Can it be Prudent or Rational to truſt ſuch a Man again, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ho <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> once diſcarded among other things for ſo foul and Criminall a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> duty? or do we think in earneſt that Mr. <hi>W. H.</hi> is any other <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> then Hypocrites and Apoſtates uſually are, who have no Principle but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and fear; for by his behaviour after his Converſion to the very <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> or his being turned out of his place, by his almoſt totall neglect, and by his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly performance of the Offices of the Church, you may gueſs what reſpect he had for them, a Form of Prayer made him puke, he ſweat a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and at the Second Service dy'd away, and he ſtill hates every thing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Church but its Preferments, and this ſome of his Friends are ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> and ſatisfy'd to be true, tho' it may be not quite ſo far a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> I have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that for this only reaſon they abett his pretentions, in oppoſition to every thing that is either Juſt or Sacred among Men, neither can it indeed be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected that he ſhould be much a friend to poſitive Conſtitutions, which muſt needs ly flat and cold upon his Stomach, who ſcorns to be Fetter'd by thoſe Eternal reſtraints the Convictions of truth, the Laws of Eſſentiall and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable reaſon, the Adamantine tyes and obligations of nature.</p>
               <p>For my part double diligence in any Employment, is a thing which I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pretended to in my Life, but without entring into Compariſon with him. I can ſay, that I have faithfully diſcharged my truſt, or elſe have made Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion that it ſhould be done by others, when either my occaſions called me abroad, or my indiſpoſition kept me at home, or my Studies were too im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate to be deny'd my attendance upon them. For the firſt four years <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> thereabouts, there were Prayers duely twice a week, upon <hi>Wedneſdays</hi> and <hi>Frydays</hi> according to the Canon, and afterwards when this did not ſatisfy the Governors, I allowed eight Pounds yearly out of my Pocket, to which they were pleaſed of their goodneſs to add twelve more for a Competence for a Reader every Morning and Evening<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> I have viſited the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> as there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>as occaſion, and adminiſter'd the Sacrament, when I thought it fit for in that I muſt begg leave to be my own carver, and all this five years time and up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I know not that ever a Sermon was omitted once a week unleſs it
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95499:13"/> were once, when I fell ill in the midſt of the Prayers and could not go tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough my whole task, and as I have done all the good I am able in the Houſe, as opportunity bath adminiſtred occaſion for it, ſo I ſhall not only ſtill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue to do it as long as I ſtay there, but as long as I live it ſhall have my good wiſhes, and all the ſmall aſſiſtances I am able to afford it, even though I be Illegally and arbitrarily diſpoſſeſt of what I have ſo long Legally enjoyed.</p>
               <p>One particular inſtance I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rave leave here to inſert of my readineſs to ſerve the Hoſpitall upon any occaſion, though it be only an expreſſion of my good will towards it, and at the ſame time an Intimation of my want of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, becauſe the deſign dropt and fell to the Ground. It is now above three years ago, as I remember, that there was a very worthy project under con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of Re building this decayed and ruinated houſe, which call<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for another Hoſpitall to receive it ſelf, and is almoſt as weak, and crazy, as any of the Patients within its Walls, the deſign went ſo far that if I am not miſinform'd, that Famous Mathematitian and Architect Sir <hi>Chriſtopher Wren,</hi> was brought hither to take an Actuall ſurvey of the building intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, which upon ſo large and ſpatious a plat of Ground improved by the great <hi>Genius</hi> of that Admirable man would have made a moſt Noble and Magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent Structure. A Private contribution from one good man to another, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther among the Governors, or at Court or abroad in the world, was the way propoſed to bring this great work to perfection, which I confeſs I looked up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to be <hi>Magnae molis,</hi> a thing of great labour and difficulty, like the work it ſelf, and that the Fatigue and Tediouſneſs of ſuch a Collection, (eſpecially when <hi>Chelſey</hi> Colledge and other publique buildings, which I knew of, had Exhauſted ſo much) would give a damp and diſcouragement to the under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taking, not but that conſiderable ſums might have been advanced this way, but to help the buſineſs forward I was for procuring a brief to be read in all Churches and Chappells thorough the Kingdom, the whole Kingdom being more or leſs obliged to the Charity of this Houſe, and concerned in Grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude and in proſpect of what future occaſion there might be of applying to it for the relief of their Sick or wounded, as well as out of a publick Principle of Chriſtianity and good nature, to contribute to ſo worthy and uſefull a deſign. This I Communicated in diſcourſe to Mr. <hi>Seymour,</hi> who ſo well ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved it, that he immediately imparted it to ſome others, and I, while the fancy was warm and freſh within me, drew up, as well as I could, the ſor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of a brief, to be corrected and altered by ſuch as underſtood the methods of ſuch things better than I do, which I have ſtill by me, but after much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe and many Conſultations, for what reaſon I know not, whether as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>practicable or unſeaſonable at that time, the thing fell aſleep and paſt off <hi>in Fumo</hi> without any effect. I mention this, I ſay, only to ſhow my good will to the Houſe, and I deſire Mr <hi>H.</hi> during his four years Reign and reſidence at his Court at <hi>Clapham</hi> to give ſuch another inſtance of his, and I do here a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain Solemnly proteſt that no ill uſage which I have never deſerved, ſhall ever alienate my affection from this Houſe, but that I will always Remember, upon all occaſions, the kindneſs and ſupport I have received from it, without reflecting upon the wrongs and Injuries that are or have been done me.</p>
               <p>So much for Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his not being in Orders and for his tacit conſent, a ſort of conſent which God abhorrs and utterly proteſts againſt, that ever it ſhould be given to unlawfull things. <hi>Theſe things haſt thou done,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>and I held my Tongue, and thou thoughteſt wickedly, that I am even ſuch an one as thy ſelf,</hi>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:95499:13"/> 
                  <hi>but I will reprove thee and ſet before thee the things that thou haſt done.</hi> And I muſt confeſs I do not a little wonder that the preſent Court of Aldermen ſhould ratify that Election with more then a tacit conſent, which that which was then in being, when Mr <hi>H.</hi> his Fourſcore Governours pitcht upon him for the object of their Choice, if they had taken any cognizance or received any particular Information of it, would have condemned and evacuated with the laſt degree of Scorn and Indignation, but Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> is now a Conformiſt, which he was not then, and I do really attribute this unequall proceeding in a Court of ſo great Juſtice and Honour as that is, to the miſrepreſentations of Mr <hi>H.</hi> and his Friends, and to their want of ſufficient Information in the matter.</p>
               <p>It is next to be conſidered, that when Mr <hi>H.</hi> was Ejected out of this houſe, for the Reaſons that have been already declared, it was not long before he was otherwiſe provided for, with a Freehold inſtead of an Arbitrary dependance, and with a Living of at leaſt Sixſcore Pounds a year, that being the loweſt Computation that ever I heard made of it, inſtead of a Salary of Threeſcore, dependant upon pleaſure, which Living was beſtowed upon him in pity to his Circumſtances, and out of that exceſs of Charity which is naturall to great minds, in lieu of what he was deprived of here, they believing, becauſe they were not capable of Hypocriſy themſelves, that the pretences of this Whineyard were reall, and that being ſo true a Convert to a Church which he mortally hates, it was a great piece of hardſhip and next kin to Injuſtice, upon him, to diſpoſſeſs him of his place. I know Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> is uſed to ſay, he ſaid it more then once to me and to my Wife, and he hath blown it about among all his Friends, that this Living was not given him in lieu of what he had loſt, but for ſome other reaſons beſt known to himſelf, which he is not pleaſed to diſcover, but yet this he does diſcover by this <hi>Cryptic</hi> Method, which is uſually accounted an argument of Wiſdom, that he believes me at the ſame time a moſt deſpicable fool, and that he himſelf is a moſt Flagitious, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bominable Knave, for I love dearly to call things by their right names, and if the laſt of theſe Characters eſpecially be true, he ſhould be no true Member of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which deteſts and devotes the Principles and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctices of ſuch wretched Fellows. For I appeal with great aſſurance to thoſe Reverend and Learned Gentlemen that were concerned in this his new Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, whoſe great and Venerable names I will not fully by inſerting them in a juſt Satyr againſt ſo vile a Caitiff, Firſt, whether they would have ſtick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo hard to have this Hypocrite reſtored, if they had deſign'd or intended any other preferment for him, which might have been an equall or a greater ſupport then that was, I can never induce my ſelf to believe this, becauſe it would look with ſo particular, a pointed hatred againſt me, which I no more believe then I do that Mr <hi>H.</hi> is an honeſt man, and with all Imaginable franck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, Sincerity and thankfullneſs I ſpeak it, though they thought Mr <hi>H.</hi> to have been a little too hardly dealt with, I know that they are now, and I am very well ſatisfy'd they were then all my Friends, and it ſhall be my con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant endeavour, with a Proviſo againſt this Simpleton Mr <hi>H.</hi> whom I am re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved not to ſpare, and whoſe Intereſt againſt mine in this particular Caſe, I am very confident they will no longer eſpouſe, not to undeſerve the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of ſuch good opinions.</p>
               <p>Secondly, I preſume to appeal to them, and do perfectly throw my ſelf up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on their free and open anſwer to the Queſtion, whether they did not really
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95499:14"/> and purpoſely preferr Mr <hi>H.</hi> or cauſe him to be preferred to his Living in the Country upon this Conſideration and no other, that they thought him hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly treated in being ejected from hence.</p>
               <p>But without the rudeneſs of Catechizing my Superiors, the thing ſpeaks ſo plainly for it ſelf, that I might have ſpared thoſe names which nature calls him, and which all men of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>enſe muſt acknowledge to be his due, for to what purpoſe ſhould they give him another Living in Conjunction with this? the whole Salary of this was but Threeſcore pounds a year, and he muſt ſupply one of theſe places by a Curate, to whom when he had allowed an Honeſt Maintenance, what could he get? beſides, that ſomething may well be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to be loſt by Non-Reſidence upon his Country Living, for the Country people are uſually as ſharp as their Parſon, though it were Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> his own ſelf, and ſomething muſt be pay'd here for rent, had he lived out of the Hoſpitall, as I take it for granted he would never have lived in it, any more then he did before, for I ſee not what inducement there could be to alter his mind, and of what advantage, then could the Hoſpitall have been at the Foot of this Account? or would it not rather have been his Intereſt as well as duty, to have thrown up this, leaving it free for me or any body elſe, and to have retired into his Country Living, there to have ſpent the remainder of his days, as <hi>Nuns</hi> that were no <hi>Nuns</hi> formerly do in a Cloyſter; in Beads and Penances for his <hi>Abingdon</hi> Sermon, and for the Hypocriſy of his pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Converſion, and all the other ſins of his Life? I ſay, it was his duty no leſs then his intereſt, and thereby hangs a tale, for you muſt know this Mr <hi>H.</hi> among other of his works, writ a very Pious and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Treatiſe againſt Pluralities and Non-Reſidence, and he could not hold his Living and his Hoſpitall together without confuting his book. For two Livings I ſuppoſe, will be granted to be a Plurality, and it is a known Maxim in the <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Philoſophy, which is like Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> for that, that it is ſometimes in the right, though it be but very ſeldom, that one and the ſame numericall, and Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duall body cannot be preſent in two Places at once, and from thence Non-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence muſt unavoidably have followed. So that Mr. <hi>H.</hi> in this Caſe had no more choice then this, he muſt either have affronted his Conſcience (and what a Conſcience is that that would Proſtitute it ſelf for ſo very ſmall an ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage, as I have computed this would have amounted too) or he muſt have relinquiſht one of his places, or reca<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ted his book and own himſelf to have written or rather bray'd Hereſy before he was aware, like the dull <hi>animal</hi> that mumbles Thiſtles. I grant indeed that in law theſe two preferments would have made no plurality, becauſe one of them is not in the legall ſtile properly term'd <hi>cura animarum,</hi> but yet there are Souls in one place as well as in the other, and it may be more in this then in his Country Living, ſo that it is a plurality in Conſcience though not in Law, and I challenge him to ſhew me one argument in his Book, that does not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ly in his face and call him by thoſe names which I will not give my ſelf the liberty to uſe, being ſenſible I have called him but too ſeverely already, for which I beg his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe, as I hope he will think it but juſt and honeſt to beg mine too, for ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given me ſo Foul a Provocation, by endeavouring to eject me out of what I legally and rightfully enjoy, though he himſelf can get nothing by the bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, which is infernall quinteſſence, the Devill rectify'd to his higheſt pitch, it is Malice not in words, (as he may perhaps interpret my raillery to be, a poor piece of buſineſs for a man that is robb'd of his right) but in very deed
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95499:14"/> and in truth. I ſay, he can get nothing but infamy and diſgrace among all the Catholique Church of honeſt men, for none but ſuch do properly belong to the myſticall body of Chriſt, and if this be the gain he contends for, much good may it do him, and I call it malice, becauſe I cannot call it Revenge, for Revenge is the retaliation of an injury receiv'd, but I never did him any; he delerv'd it's true to be turn'd out of his place, but I knew not the man nor his place neither, I never ſupplanted him, I ſcorn ſuch profligate and dege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerous acts, I was actually appointed in his ſtead by the kindneſs of my friends, before I knew the leaſt Syllable or letter that any ſuch thing was deſign'd, and if I had not had it, it is undoubtedly certain that ſome body elſe muſt, ſo that I in particular was ſo far from doing him any injuſtice, that my very ſucceeding him really did him no harm, ſince it muſt have been done by ſome body elſe, if it had not been done by me, and yet if providence had not juſt then pointed out that refuge for me to fly to, my affairs were brought to that extremity that I was in danger of immediate ruine, ſo that he is angry with providence for providing for my ſafety, as it did afterwards more plentifully for his, he is angry with me for giving my ſelf up to the Guidance and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of thoſe happy Starrs that would not ſee me periſh with Hunger and Cold, and he makes it now his buſineſs to procure my ruine, though at the ſame time he knows, he can get nothing by it, but the odious reputation of the worſt of men, ſo that if this be not malice, there is no ſuch thing, and if ever man were excuſeable for a ſharp invective upon an invererate, but cauſeleſs Enemy, 'tis I.</p>
               <p>But ſaith Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> as to the buſineſs of Pluralities, it was his own eva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion when I urg'd it to him, Sauce for a <hi>Gooſe</hi> is Sauce for a <hi>Gander,</hi> why may not I be a Pluraliſt, as well as you? No Mr. <hi>Hughes,</hi> it is not the ſame caſe, for I never writ agrinſt pluralities, as you have done, and beſides you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not accuſe me of non-reſidence, from whence all your arguments, if you would ſpeak any thing that looks like ſenſe, muſt of neceſſity derive their force, and by this you made the Hoſpital a Plurality though it were but one place: It is not a plurality in law, becauſe neither of the Places is <hi>cum cura animar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> in the legall ſtile, nor in Conſcience, (though I am for Pluralities in a ſober ſenſe, if I knew how to come at them) becauſe they are contiguous, and may both very well be ſufficiently taken care of, even in the Judgment of thoſe that quarrell moſt at ſuch things, by the ſame Perſon, it is after the Example of St <hi>Bartholomew</hi>'s it ſelf, which is the older Foundation of the two, where both the Hoſpitall and Pariſh are United, it is purſuant to the reaſon and intention of that Act of Parliament, by which ſmall Livings were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and joyn'd together after the Fire of <hi>London,</hi> and there is no doubt but if that fatall Calamity had ſpread it ſelf ſo far, as by Gods great Mercy it did not, the ſame proviſion upon the ſame ground would have been made here, and Laſtly the Juſtice and even neceſſity of it is acknowledged by the Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Dr. <hi>Burnet,</hi> now the Right Reverend Lord Biſhop Elect of <hi>Sar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>m,</hi> in his Sermon before the <hi>Commons</hi> at the beginning of this preſent Parliament, where among other things that are managed like himſelf, with an Air and vigour peculiar to their Author, he piouſly recommends the encouragement of the Clergy and the encreaſing of ſmall Livings for their ſupport; I know not whether Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> hath read that Sermon or no, but I am ſure he dare not read his two other Admirable diſcourſes, from the Pulpi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, The <hi>Royall Martyr,</hi> I mean, and the <hi>Dutifull Subject,</hi> for fear of reflecting too ſeverely upon his own
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95499:15"/> doubty Performance, to be admired for nothing that I know of, but that it is ſo reſinedly, ſo admirably wicked, His <hi>Abingdon</hi> Law, his Banqueting houſe Entertainment, more Cruell then thoſe of <hi>Progne</hi> and <hi>Thyeſtes</hi> wherein he careſs'd himſelf and entertain'd his Friends (<hi>O ſcelus! O Flagitium!</hi>) with the Mangled and bleeding Father of his Country.</p>
               <p>I ſhall conclude this whole matter with theſe two things. Firſt, I deſire that it may be taken notice, that when upon the death of the Reverend &amp; my late dear friend Mr <hi>Sowton,</hi> the Pariſh of St. <hi>Thomas</hi>'s became void, his Majeſty King <hi>James</hi> the Second, was pleaſed upon a Repreſentation of the Equity of my Caſe to him, the Hoſpitall alone not affording a ſufficient maintenance for a Clergy Man in this Town, to withdraw a Mandate granted in behalf of ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in my Favour, and accordingly upon this notice that it was his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties pleaſure, as I think a plainer Indication of it could not poſſibly be given, I had an Order from the Commiſſioners for the Union, that is, in effect I had two Legall Orders for the place of Hoſpitaller, and one for the Pariſh, the lat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of which two Orders was with his Majeſties particular knowledge and Approbation, ſo that it was his own Act in his own Houſe, and what more Legall choice then this there can be, where the King meddles with nothing but what is Legally in his own diſpoſall, as this matter of the Union manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly was, I would be glad to be informed. For it is plain that this was not only the Act of the Commiſſioners, who gave their conſent, as indeed they could not well deny it, to what they knew to be the Kings pleaſure, but more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately and expreſly of the King himſelf, who if he did many Arbitrary things, which I neither can nor will defend, though in Gratitude I ought not to upbraid him with them, yet I hope the Legall Acts of a Lawfull and right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full King, as all men will acknowledge that Prince to have been at that time, ought not to be the leſs binding and valid, becauſe afterwards, (for this was in the firſt year of his Reign) he did ſeveral things which were Arbitrary and Illegall. If a Mandate be ſent down to any Colledge in either Univerſity for the admitting of a Maſter or Fellow who could not Statutably be choſen, ſuppoſing he ly under no incapacities by Act of Parliament or by the known Laws of the Realm, this Mandate according to the common Practice of the Univerſity takes place without any more ado, unleſs there be ſome great ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptions againſt the Perſon, or elſe ſome other more deſerving or more deſira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Perſon be precluded by it, in which Caſe they uſually repreſent back again to the King, and Endeavour to get it withdrawn, not that they diſpute the Kings Power, but that they endeavour to encline his will to a choice more agreeable and pleaſing to themſelves, or more for the Intereſt and Honour of their Society, in deferrence to which it is very well known that they do ſometimes Court a Mandate inſtead of refuſing it, and are glad in ſuch Caſes where their local Statutes are a little too hard upon Merit, that the King in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpoſeth his Authority Royall for the Encouragement of Arts and the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vancement of Learning, and that in thoſe Colledges that are not of Royall Foundation, &amp; yet by ſuch Mandates a Freehold is convey'd, &amp; the Perſon in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted hath an equall right, in at common acceptation, with any other Member whoſoever. But whatever exceptions may poſſibly be offer'd againſt this pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice in the Univerſities, tho' nothing hath been in repetition more frequent, ever ſince I knew what the Univerſity was, and a great while before, nor any thing in Fact more firm then ſuch inveſtitures by the King's letter, yet no man ſure will diſpute the Kings Prerogative in his own Foundation,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95499:15"/> and a Foundation in the Charter, of which there is an expreſs reſervation to himſelf and Succeſſors to inſpect and viſit at all times hereafter, and where the King hath an undoubted and unqueſtionable right of putting in and putting out when he pleaſes, provided they be not unqualify'd by law for their em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments which was <hi>Mr. H's</hi> Caſe, when he came firſt to this houſe, who was ſo unqualify'd by law for his place, that even the King himſelf could not diſpenſe with him; in ſuch an houſe as this, I ſuppoſe it will be grant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that the Kings Mandate ought to take place, and I had more then a man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date, if more then that can be, becauſe a mandate was recalled for my ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage. I had the concurrence of the King and Commi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ioners, for an union of the two places, that is, for an actuall poſſeſſion and injoyment of them both, and what firmer title to a thing of this nature there can be I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not Imagine, and certainly the law would have done very weakly to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſt the King with the diſpoſall of ſo many and ſo great Spirituall prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, ſo as to intitle the perſons on whom they are conferred to a Free-hold in the ſame, if at the ſame time he ſhall not be allowed to place a Chaplain in his own houſe, of his own or his Royall Anceſtors Foundation, in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutions of which he hath expreſsly reſerved a right of inſpection and regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to himſelf.</p>
               <p>The Second thing I hinted at, with which I ſhall ſhut up all, is what I have already pretty largely inſiſted upon, but cannot in this cauſe be too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently repeated, or too heedfully attended to, and that is, that the diſſolution of the Commiſſion by which this regulation was made, doth not at all affect the regulation it ſelf, ſo as that muſt of neceſſity be diſſolved together with it, for this were to ſuppoſe that an houſe can be no ſooner built, but it muſt tum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and fall down again, as ſoon as the Scaffolds, by the help of which it was erected, are removed, and the Artificers diſperſt and gone away, whereas then indeed it is, and not till then that the houſe appears in it's true Beauty and Strength.</p>
               <p>It hath been prov'd ſufficiently already that the King had always a power of viſiting this houſe, even though the City Charter had ſtood, ſo that though the adminiſtration of the City and the viſitation of this houſe were both of them intruſted with the ſame Commiſſioners, yet they were manifeſtly two Commiſſions tack't together that were in themſelves diſtinct from one ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and the King if he had pleas'd, might have put the viſitation of this houſe at that time into other hands, and as ſoon as the regulation had been perfect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, he might have diſſolved the Commiſſion, but what a mock regulation had this been? what a Scandall and Contempt would it have brought upon ſuch a regulating deſign as this, if the regulation had been diſſolved together with it? or indeed to what purpoſe would ſuch a regulation have been? and yet if it be not actually diſſolved upon the diſſolution of the Commiſſion it ſelf, then the Governours and Officers muſt ſtand as they were, till they are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placed by the ſame or an equall power, becauſe in this it was that the regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation conſiſted.</p>
               <p>Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> by her Commiſſioners viſited the Univerſities, altered their Statutes and made many great and laſting regulations which remain to this day, notwithſtanding the Commiſſion be not only diſſolved, but the Commiſſioners long ſince dead and mouldered away to duſt in their graves. And ſo in the late Caſe of <hi>Magdalen College,</hi> there is no man of common ſenſe can queſtion but if the Commiſſion had been legall or managed and purſued
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95499:16"/> after a Legall manner, but the Regulation would have been valid, though the Commiſſion had expired, after the buſineſs, it was intended for, had been done, otherwiſe it would have been a Commiſſion as Ridiculous and abſurd, as it is acknowledged to have been Arbitrary and Illegall.</p>
               <p>This is what I have to ſay for my ſelf and my Friends and Fellow-Servants in this houſe, but againſt Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> in particular all things are ſo ſtrong, and run upon him with ſo fierce a Stream, that I ſuſpect the ſoundneſs of his underſtanding for offering to attempt a thing in which he could reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propoſe nothing but infamy and diſgrace to himſelf, he ſeems to me to be got into the predicament of Dr <hi>Rolls,</hi> and that even <hi>Hellebore</hi> and <hi>Anticyra</hi> it ſelf, are unable to reſtore him to his right mind, ſo far are his Wits run a Woolgathering from it.</p>
               <p>And now upon the whole matter I am very ſure of the Victory, which I have allready obtain'd by dint of Argument againſt him, though he may poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibly run away with the Triumph, and I had much rather loſe ſo fair a cauſe as mine is, then gain a Scandalous Conqueſt, by ſucceeding in his</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Victrix c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſa Deis placuit, ſed victa Catoni.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>I Have two things further to add, which occur-now newly to my mind, and are, I think, material to the purpoſe, the Firſt as to the Regulation in generall, the deſign of which ſeems to have been, to diſplace all that were not at that time Communicants of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that being the intereſt which the Court thought fit at that juncture to encourage: It is not my bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs in this place to weigh the Merits of Cauſes or of Perſons, neither do I at all intend by this to reflect upon the Perſons Ejected, as if they were defective in the diſcharge of their truſt, the contrary of which, bating only what con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerns my Friend Mr <hi>Hughes,</hi> is that which I did always and do ſtill very firmly believe; but this I ſay, that by this it appears, that it was a Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion not only made by him, that had a Legall right to do it, of which I have already ſpoken very largely, but it was alſo ſuch a Regulation, as the Laws of this Land, if they did not Expicitely enjoyn, yet they did manifeſtly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage and abett, it being very incongruous to proſecute the ſame Perſons upon account of their Religion, which was no more then what the Laws put in Execution would certainly have done, and yet at the ſame time to reward them with publick Salaries, for the ſame ſervices, that Members of the Eſtabliſh'd Communion were capable of performing with equall, if not greater advantage to the Houſe, I ſay, greater, in reference to that part of the Governors, to whom their ſervice will always be moſt acceptable, who have without queſtion, the moſt of the Gentleman in them, and will at the long run, prove the moſt generous Benefactors to us, if they be not diſobliged, for he hath no Honour that hath no reſentment. I appeal to the greateſt fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers of Mr. <hi>H.</hi> and others, if a ſet of <hi>Papiſts</hi> were put into the Houſe, to fill up the reſpective Offices belonging to it, whether they would then grumble at a Royall Regulation, whether they would not allow the King
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95499:16"/> a Power of Viſiting in this Caſe? whether they would not agree, that the Ejection of ſuch Perſons, was not only neceſſary, but Legall too? and Laſtly whether they would not think it a very unreaſonable thing, that they that ſtand impeached and Condemned by ſo many Laws, ſhould be Encouraged with Salaries out of the publique Kevenue, and preferred before thoſe, upon whom the Laws never look but with a kind and favourable aſpect? I do not in this make any odious compariſon betwixt a <hi>Papiſt</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Diſſenter, as if the one were as much to be diſcountenanced as the other, but yet I chal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lenge any man to ſhew a reaſon, why a <hi>Papiſt</hi> ſhould be Ejected, which will not, in the dry conſequence and Inference of the matter, affect and reach a <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant</hi> Diſſenter, to whoſe diſſent I cannot help it that the Laws are no friends, and that he cannot be encouraged in an affair of this Nature, without ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing that ſquints towards a diſpenſing Power. Not to preferr can never be thought a piece of Perſecution, and the Government will always chuſe its own Servants, as it is but reaſon it ſhould, ſo that this Regulation being made by a Legall Power &amp; for a reaſon agreeable to the Laws. I think it hath all the Validity and Strength, that any Act in the World can be ſuppoſed to have.</p>
               <p>Secondly, the ſecond thing I muſt Suggeſt, is only in Fayrneſs to the other Side, that I may not ſeem to conceal or ſmuggle any thing, that hath a fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vorable Appearance towards them. It is, that our Orders run only during Pleaſure, therefore the Queſtion is, upon the Diſſolution of the Commiſſion, whether that pleaſure be not diſſolved, and I anſwer not, becauſe firſt <hi>durante beneplacito</hi> ſignifies till that Court otherwiſe determine, which they never did. Secondly, though theſe expreſs words had not been inſerted, yet the thing it ſelf was plainly ſuppoſed, we being all of us at the pleaſure of that Court and of the King from whom they derived their Commiſſion, and holding by no other Tenure, ſo that all the queſtion here is, whether all their Acts were vacated by their diſſolution, which I conceive they were not, and I hope I have given ſome reaſon for it.</p>
               <p>Thirdly and Laſtly, that pleaſure, being a reall Power, can never dye, like matter and motion that are always equall and the ſame taken in the groſs, neither can a greater pleaſure be ſwallowed up in a leſs, any more then a greater quantity can be, and for this reaſon the pleaſure or Power of the Commiſſioners can never be the pleaſure or Power of the Court of Aldermen, but returns back again to its Eountain the King, to whoſe Royall Juſtice, Goodneſs and Wiſdom, I am very willing to referr my Cauſe, if Mr <hi>Hughes</hi> think fit to make his appeal to it, In the mean time I would willingly ſee a rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, before I abandon and relinquiſh my poſſeſſion.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
